MATLAB Signal Generator and Noise Analysis Code Explanation

Overview
This MATLAB script simulates a signal generator project tasked with producing square and sine waves at three specific frequencies derived from a student number. The script implements filtering, noise addition, recovery, and spectral analysis.

Functions
quadratic_fft_peak_interp(mag, f_axis)
	This helper function performs quadratic interpolation on the FFT magnitude 	spectrum (mag) around the maximum spectral peak to refine the frequency estimate 	beyond the raw FFT bin resolution. Given the frequency axis vector f_axis, it fits 	a parabola to the peak and its adjacent bins and returns an interpolated frequency 	estimate f_est.

Main Code Sections
SECTION 1 – Input and Frequency Extraction
	The user is prompted to input their student number.
	Numeric digits are extracted, non-zero digits are isolated.
	The last three non-zero digits are used to derive frequencies:
	These frequencies are displayed and stored for signal generation.

SECTION 2 – Signal Generation and Processing
	Sampling frequency 
	Fs=10,000 Hz and duration 1 second are set.
	For each frequency 
	Generate a square wave at 
	Generate a sine wave for reference (not used in output).
	Design a 6th order Butterworth low-pass filter with cutoff = 1.5×f0
	Filter the square wave using zero-phase filtering (filtfilt) to generate the soft 	sine wave approximation.

SECTION 3 – Noise Addition and Recovery
	Add Additive White Gaussian Noise (AWGN) at 10 dB SNR to simulate channel effects.
	Apply same Butterworth filter with filtfilt on noisy signal to attempt noise 	recovery.

SECTION 4 – Visualization
	Calculate sample range corresponding to showing 1 to 5 cycles for timing plots.
	Plot six subplots per frequency showing:
	Original square wave.

	Soft filtered sine wave.

	FFT magnitude of square wave.

	FFT magnitude of filtered wave.

	Clean vs noisy wave in time domain.

	Noisy vs recovered wave in time domain.

	Titles, labels, grids, legends are properly set for clarity.

SECTION 5 – Performance Metrics
	Compute power of clean and noisy signals to estimate input SNR.

	Compute power of noise before and after clean filtering to estimate noise 	reduction gain.

	Use quadratic FFT peak interpolation to get refined estimated signal frequency.

	Print SNR and frequency error information.

	Parameter Calculations and Justifications
	Sampling frequency of 10 kHz is high enough for Nyquist criterion given max 	expected frequency 100s of Hz.

	Duration of 1 second allows sufficient frequency resolution in FFT for clear 	spectral analysis.

	Filter cutoff at 1.4× fundamental prevents attenuating main frequency while 	suppressing harmonics effectively.

	Use of filtfilt zero-phase filtering removes phase distortion compared to causal 	filtering.

	Noise level at 10 dB SNR provides a moderate, realistic noise challenge.

Program Flow Summary
	Input Student Number → Extract Frequencies

		Loop over each frequency:

	a. Generate square & sine waves
b. Design and apply Butterworth filter for smoothing
	c. Add noise and recover signal
	d. Plot all waveforms and spectra
e. Compute and print SNR, frequency accuracy metrics

Repeat until all frequencies processed